בוקר טוב, Boker tov, good morning, גמר חתימה טובה, G'mar chasima tova,
good הושענא רבה, Hoshana Rabba, we pick up today's דף daf is
פ"ז, Peh Zayin, 87, and we have a few משניות, mishnayot, a
few דפים dapim on זקן ממרא. Zaken Mamre. This is where זקן
ממרא Zaken Mamre gets discussed in ש"ס. Shas. It's one of the
people who get חנק. chenek. And it picks up with a משנה
mishna on the bottom of פ"ו עמוד ב'. Peh Vav Amud Bet.
זקן ממרא, Zaken Mamre, the rebellious elder. על
פי בית דין. Al pi Beis Din. So first of all, he's
rebelling against the authority of the
בית דין. Beis Din. שנאמר, She-ne'emar, כי יפלא ממך דבר למשפט. Ki
yipale mimcha davar lamishpat. It's very interesting, here the משנה mishna incorporates
in sort of explicating the פסוקים, pesukim, which we really have not
had yet, certainly not an extensive explication. If a matter is hidden
from you, דבר למשפט, davar lamishpat, so somehow that's proving that it's
rebelling against the בית דין Beis Din because, I mean later it
says וקמת ועלית אל המקום Vekamta ve'alita el hamakom האיש אשר יעשה
בזדון לבלתי שמוע אל השופט. Ha'ish asher ya'aseh b'zadon l'vilti shemo'a el
hashofet. It's very clear in the context that he's rebelling against the
בית דין. Beis Din. I really don't understand why he qualifies it.
It doesn't say like בן סורר ומורה Ben Sorer u-Moreh על פי
אביו ואמו, al pi aviv v'imo, you know, I mean the context
is pretty clear. Here it's just like it needs to emphasize that
it's על פי בית דין al pi Beis Din and it took
a פסוק pasuk to support it. Anyway, שלושה בתי דינים היו שם.
Shlosha Batei Dinim hayu sham. Now we get into a discussion which
in the ירושלמי Yerushalmi brought this in way at the beginning of
the מסכת masechet about sort of the hierarchy of the courts and
why, you know, you really can't sort of go to a court
of appeals if you didn't like your judgment. But if the court
itself didn't know the answer, they could appeal to a higher court.
Okay, and there were three, so there's a whole discussion about the
court in your city doesn't know, then they go to the regional
court, the regional court doesn't know, then they bring it to ירושלים
Yerushalayim and so on. This sort of focuses us straight on the
בתי דינים Batei Dinim that are in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, and not even
in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, but on הר הבית. Har HaBayit. And even there,
there are three levels. שלושה בתי דינים היו שם, Shlosha Batei Dinim
hayu sham, there were three בתי דינים Batei Dinim in ירושלים, Yerushalayim,
excuse me, הר הבית. Har HaBayit. אחד יושב על פתח הר הבית,
Echad yoshev al petach Har HaBayit, one by the opening of הר
הבית, Har HaBayit, ואחד יושב על פתח עזרה, ve-echad yoshev al petach
Azara, one right by before you would enter into the עזרה, Azara,
the עזרת ישראל, Ezrat Yisrael, ואחד יושב בלשכת הגזית, ve-echad yoshev be-Lishkat
HaGazit, and the last one was in the לשכת הגזית, Lishkat HaGazit,
which was half in the עזרה Azara and half like, and you
know and half out. I think רש"י Rashi says שבנויה בתוך עזרה
חציו בקודש וחציו בחול. she-b'nuya b'toch Azara chetzyo b'kodesh v'chetzyo b'chol. Okay,
so, I mean
take a look at רש"י, Rashi, right? רש"י Rashi says three lines
down in the wide lines, אחד יושב פתח הר הבית: הוא שער
המזרחי שפנים מן החיל לפני עזרת נשים. Echad yoshev petach Har HaBayit:
hu sha'ar hamizrachi she-p'nim min hachel lifnei Ezrat Nashim. So that is,
right, you would basically have,
okay, so if this is east here, okay, so here anyway you
would have, right, this would be the קודש קודשים, Kodesh Kodashim, this
would be the היכל, Heichal, this would be the אולם, Ulam,
here you'd have your מזבח, mizbeach, okay, here you'd have this, so
this would be like עזרת כהנים, Ezrat Kohanim, oops, here you'd have
your עזרת
ישראל, Ezrat Yisrael, okay, all of this is technically the עזרה, Azara,
alright, and then you would have the,
this is like the actual בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, then you'd have
the עזרת נשים, Ezrat Nashim, have these sort of chambers here, and
then you'd have this wall that sort of surrounds the whole thing
and that would be called the חיל, Chel, okay. So where would
these various בתי דינים Batei Dinim be found? So רש"י Rashi says,
so one is פתח הר
הבית, petach Har HaBayit, הוא שער המזרחי שפנים מן החיל לפני עזרת
נשים. hu sha'ar hamizrachi she-p'nim min hachel lifnei Ezrat Nashim. So one
of them would be here, okay, and the,
and ואחד יושב למעלה ממנו כשעברו עזרת נשים ובאים
לפני עזרת ישראל. v'echad yoshev l'ma'ala mimenu k'she-avru Ezrat Nashim u-va'im lifnei
Ezrat Yisrael. So רש"י Rashi sort of says before they got to
עזרת ישראל, Ezrat Yisrael, so not exactly clear where, but let's just
sort of arbitrarily say it was something like here. I don't know
if it would be right in the way of the, in the
center. And then the one in the לשכת הגזית Lishkat HaGazit שבנויה
בתוך עזרה חציו בקודש וחציו בחול. she-b'nuya b'toch Azara chetzyo b'kodesh v'chetzyo
b'chol. And in מסכת יומא, Masechet Yoma, so because they sat, they
couldn't actually
have like, what do you call it, had been all in the
עזרה Azara because you can't sit in the עזרה, Azara, so half
of it has to be בחול, b'chol, חול chol means somewhere like,
again, I'd have to, I didn't look at a picture beforehand. But
anyway, somehow it would be something like this. Okay, so and this
would be the, this is the לשכת הגזית Lishkat HaGazit and this
is where the סנהדרין Sanhedrin would sit. So it's ממש mamash on
הר הבית, Har HaBayit, partly, actually in the space of the קודש
קודשים, Kodesh Kodashim, of the עזרה Azara of the actual בית המקדש,
Beis HaMikdash, but partly not, which basically allows them to
sit.
All right, now, ובאים לזה שעל פתח... u-va'im l'zeh she-al petach... so
if there was a dispute, so apparently what he imagines is, right,
there was in the local court there was a dispute what the
law was, and they would have and they went and they and
they kept on pushing it up to a higher court to get
a final ruling. Okay, what's also not clear is, is that was
the dispute that it was like, was it it seems because it's
always one guy who's refusing to accept the authority, but why didn't
they just outvote him? You know, why didn't they just say, okay,
it's two to one or it's whatever it is, it's twenty-two to
one or whatever, you're outvoted. Somehow it seems that because he says
no, I'm right, I'm right, I refuse to whatever, that he can
like force them to go to a higher court to get an
official ruling. But it was not just, this was a person on
the בית דין, Beis Din, not actually the person who's being prosecuted,
right? If it was just the person being prosecuted, you go by
the רוב. rov. But if it's like it seems, again it doesn't
spell it out, but that's really what we it's interesting to imagine.
What's the dynamic? Right, we normally take a vote, is this guy
חייב מיתה? chayav misah? Okay, just, you know, thirteen to ten, yes,
חייב מיתה, chayav misah, end of story. But if you have twenty-two
to one and one guy says, no, it's not end of story,
I refuse to agree, I think you're all making a big mistake.
But it doesn't give us that dynamic, right? But somehow he can
then push it to a higher court. One minute. So it says
ובאנו לזה שפתח הר הבית, uva'inu lizeh she-petach Har HaBayit, ואומר כך
דרשתי וכך דרשו חברי, כך למדתי וכך למדו חברי. ve-omer kach darashti
ve-kach darshu chaverai kach limadeti ve-kach limdu chaverai. Here's how I read
it, here's how, you know, my so it sounds like he's the
one that gets to present his case, right? This minority voice who's
pushing to get this heard. He says, look, here's how I understand
the פסוקים, psukim, here's how they understand it. כך למדתי וכך למדו
חברי, kach limadeti ve-kach limdu chaverai. here's how I learned it, here's
how they learned it. Okay, אם שמעו, im sham'u, now if this
court, it's interesting, like what, and the people that are opposing him
don't get to voice for themselves what their whole approach is, like
he presents it all on his own? It's very interesting how it
stylizes this whole thing, right? אם שמעו, im sham'u, now if this
this court here, right over here, the first one, right, if they
heard, if they have a tradition about this, אומרים להם omerim lahem
or אומרים, omerim, they say. You know, this is our tradition. ואם
לאו, ve-im lav, and if they didn't have a tradition, באים להם
לאותן שעל פתח העזרה. ba'im lahem le-otan she-al petach ha-azarah. Then they
come to the then they bring it to the next one. Now,
again, what's bizarre here is like the fact that he distinguishes between
כך דרשתי kach darashti and כך למדתי, kach limadeti, okay, shows that
we're dealing with two types of ways in which you can make
law, right? One is by this is how I interpret it based
on my own understanding of the פסוקים, psukim, the more sort of
creative approach, and the other is this is my tradition how to
read it, right? כך למדתי. kach limadeti.
So, why when this court listens to it, let's so they didn't
שמעו, sham'u, they didn't have a tradition. Who cares so okay, they
didn't have a tradition, but maybe the whole court is in an
agreement that he's wrong? We don't have a tradition about this, let's
look at the פסוקים, psukim, we're all going to take a vote,
it's twenty-three to one or whatever, you you know, it's twenty-three, we're
all even a consensus, you're wrong. It seems like, by just by
purely the way it's structuring it here, that that if they don't
have an explicit tradition, then he can still reject it. That's just
how you're interpreting it. That's just your human intellect. How who says
you're right? I still think you're making a mistake. I need the
highest court to make a final decision, right? I was anyway outvoted
back in my hometown, twenty-two to one or whatever, I don't accept
that, okay? I'll only so it sounds like the only thing they
could say to end the discussion here is we have an explicit
tradition against you. Okay, and if not, even if they're all saying
he's wrong, he gets to take it to the next level. ואם
לאו באים להם לאותן שעל פתח העזרה, ve-im lav ba'im lahem le-otan
she-al petach ha-azarah,
they come to the next one. ואומר כך דרשתי וכך דרשו חברי
ve-omer kach darashti ve-kach darshu chaverai, כך למדתי וכך למדו חברי. kach
limadeti ve-kach limdu chaverai, אם
שמעו, im sham'u, same story. The high level court, if they have
a tradition, אומרים להם omerim lahem or אומרים לו, omerim lo, whatever,
or אומרים להם, omerim lahem, they say it to them. ואם לאו,
ve-im lav, if they don't have a tradition, even if they all
think he's wrong, אלו ואלו באים לבית דין הגדול שבלשכת הגזית. elu
va-elu ba'im le-Beis Din HaGadol she-be-Lishkat HaGazit. They come to the Chamber
of Hewn Stone, שממנו יצא תורה לכל ישראל. she-mimenu yetze Torah le-chol
Yisrael. That is the ultimate seat of authority for all of the
Jewish people. שנאמר מהמקום אשר יבחר השם. shenemar mi-ha-makom asher yivchar Hashem.
From that place that God will choose, like the idea God has
chosen not only the place for the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash but
also like designated that the בית דין Beis Din sitting there is
the source of all legal authority. Now, and they rule against him.
Now, of course, what's missing here is that what do they say
to him? Do they say we have a tradition? Or did they
just say or once you get to the highest court it doesn't
matter if they have a tradition. Even if they don't have a
tradition, they get to decide. So even if it's their intellect against
his intellect, at the end of the day, their decision is the
final one, and that's what it seems like. מכך הוראה יוצאת, mi-kach
hora'ah yotzei, and it doesn't matter. Now, of course, what's what happens
if, by the way, let's say they came to the בית דין
הגדול Beis Din HaGadol and they took a vote, and it was
like, you know, thirty-six thought he was wrong and thirty-five thought he
was right? You know, or I don't know, thirty-seven and thirty-four. Is
that, you know, do you still go by majority rules there? Until
now you haven't been going to majority rule, he gets to keep
on demanding a higher and higher court. But once you get to...
But once you get to בית דין הגדול, Beis Din Hagadol, not
only does it seem like they don't need an explicit tradition, but
it even seems like presumably they would go by the normal principles
of majority rule. At the end of the day, that is the
final arbiter, and even if it's based on intellect, and even if
it's based on a vote, right, once they make the decision, that
ends the discussion. Yes. But Rabbi Eliezer got
outvoted. It didn't seem like it was outvoted on the basis of
tradition. Right, exactly, and he was famous for adhering only to his
tradition. Right, so once you get to בית דין הגדול, Beis Din
Hagadol, it sounds like then, until that point, there's something, I don't
know, very beautiful and powerful about that. Until you get to the
final arbiters, any individual can continue to say, "I think you people
are making a mistake." And at the end of the day, if
you don't have an explicit tradition, you know, maybe I'm right and
you're wrong, right? So it's only when you get to the final
arbiters that somebody, there has to be, legally there has to be
an end to the discussion. Even if it's true that you are
right and they're wrong, they have the final say, right? And that's
what happens when you get to בית דין הגדול. Beis Din Hagadol.
Okay, so, okay, and then שנאמר, shene'emar, fine. חזר לעירו. Chazar l'iro.
So they outvoted him. So then he went back home. שנה ולמד
בדרך שהיה לומד, Shana v'limmed baderech shehaya lomed,
if he goes and continues to teach the way he was learning
before, פטור. patur. He can go ahead and say, "Look guys, here's
what I think the הלכה halacha is. I know what בית דין
Beis Din פסק, paskened, but I think that they're still making a
mistake. I know that that's the הלכה. halacha. I'm not saying it's
not the הלכה, halacha, but I'm telling you I don't think it
should be the הלכה. halacha. Here's what the real הלכה halacha should
be." Then he's exempt. ואם הורה לעשות, V'im hora la'asos, the only
thing that he can do to undermine their authority and to be
a זקן ממרא Zaken Mamre is to say, "You listen to me,
don't listen to them. This is the הלכה halacha you should follow."
Then חייב. chayav. שנאמר והאיש אשר יעשה בזדון, Shene'emar v'haish asher ya'aseh
b'zadon,
so they're reading אשר יעשה, asher ya'aseh, that it's not just what
he says verbally, but it turns into action. אינו חייב עד שיורה
לעשות, Eino chayav ad sheyoreh la'asos, he has to rule in a
way that translates into action. Okay, so this is, I think, extremely
powerful about what it says about sort of the rights of intellectual
freedom, right? He is completely welcome to go and to from here
till his dying day say that he thinks בית דין Beis Din
is making a terrible mistake and here's what he thinks the הלכה
halacha should be, as long as he doesn't say, "Listen to me
and don't listen to them." As long as he says, "Of course
as a matter of הלכה, halacha, you listen to them, but they
don't know what they're talking about and they're making a terrible mistake
and here's why I'm right and they're wrong, but what they say
is the הלכה." halacha. Right? At the end of the day, it's
not about objective right and wrong, it's about who gets to decide
what is the binding law. Okay, but because of that respect of
intellectual sort of independence or you know freedom, we let him go
back and say what he's saying, and we also let him keep
on pushing it until they get to בית דין הגדול, Beis Din
Hagadol, right? And no matter how many people are overruling him until
they get to בית דין הגדול, Beis Din Hagadol, our respect that
maybe he ultimately is, even though he's a single voice against a
million people, right, you know maybe he actually knows the truth, we're
going to allow him to keep on going until we have to
get to that final בית דין הגדול. Beis Din Hagadol. One
minute. Okay. תלמיד שהורה לעשות פטור. Talmid shehora la'asos patur. If a
person is not a like a
rabbi with סמיכה, semicha, again the סמיכה semicha of the גמרא, Gemara,
you know somebody who's considered to be at the stage of being
on a בית דין, Beis Din, he's just an apprentice, he's a
תלמיד, talmid, he hasn't officially been given the title and the status
to be on a בית דין, Beis Din, and then he says,
"Listen to me and don't listen to them," so you could think
it's worse, here's this חוצפה, chutzpah, this like פישער pisher here is
telling everybody to ignore בית דין הגדול Beis Din Hagadol and listen
to me. No, he's exempt, because since he doesn't have the status,
he's not seen as a threat. Okay? So in that case נמצאו
חומרו קולו. nimtzeu chumro kulo. The stringency against him that he's not
entitled yet to be on a בית דין Beis Din comes to
be lenient on him that he doesn't get punished because since he
doesn't yet hold that authority, he's just some like, he's fine. If
some student is saying this, nobody takes it with the same seriousness
and he's not the same degree of a threat. Yes, Charlie.
So, actually what I was not going to say, but that actually
might be relevant today because we don't have real סמיכה semicha anymore.
Yeah. But the other thing is in theory that elder who's telling
everybody the סנהדרין Sanhedrin doesn't know what they're doing, maybe he has
students who eventually get on the סנהדרין Sanhedrin and reverse that decision.
That's an interesting point
too. That's an interesting point too. If I didn't think about that,
if you keep on preaching we're not just sort of giving you
the right to voice your opinion, but ultimately with given enough time
and enough influence it actually could change the הלכה. halacha. You start
a whole legal school and whatever and eventually those people get on
the סנהדרין. Sanhedrin. It's an interesting point. Okay, תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan.
Let's see the גמרא. Gemara. כי יפלא ממך דבר, Ki yipale mimcha
davar, במופלא שבבית דין הכתוב מדבר. B'mufla shebeveis din hakasuv medaber. So
it's יפלא, yipale, something is hidden to you, but it's also the
word of מופלא. mufla. fla somehow is understand like you know like
חז"ל Chazal *Chazal* understand that word מופלא *Mufla* means somebody that's like
an expert and has an authority and is fit to be on
a בית דין beit din *Beit Din*. Okay, and he's not just
a תלמיד Talmid, *talmid*.
So that's number one what we learn from it. That's that we're
dealing with somebody who has that full authority to be on a
בית דין beit din *Beit Din*. Okay. Now so כי יפלא ממך
דבר
*Ki yippalei mimcha davar*. הכתוב מדבר *Hakatuv medaber*. ממך *mimcha*, it's hidden
from you, זה יועץ *zeh yoetz*. So now we're going to break
down every single word of this פסוק pasuk *passuk* to tell you
either the to tell you well after we've told you basically the
status of the person who's making the ruling, the types of things
that you could be ruling on that to be a to be
a זקן ממרא zaken mamre. *Zaken Mamre*. So זה יועץ *zeh yoetz*,
that's an advisor. Now what does that mean? So it sounds like
we're still describing a personal characteristic but based on the later גמרא
gemara *Gemara* we mean that it's a ruling relating to קידוש החודש
Kiddush Hachodesh *Kiddush Hachodesh*. Okay, וכן הוא אומר *vechen hu omer* and
similarly it says ממך יצא חושב על ה' רעה יועץ בליעל *mimcha
yatza choshev al Hashem ra'ah yoetz beliya'al*. From you comes out this
one who thinks against God evil who advises some like whatever you
know
the I don't even know how to translate בליעל *beliya'al*. Anyway these
terrible acts. Anyway what does that have to do with anything is
not exactly clear, okay, but we will see that the but we'll
see in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. Somehow it doesn't seem like a
good thing. But anyway somehow the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* ties it into
be a ruling about קידוש החודש Kiddush Hachodesh. *Kiddush Hachodesh*. We'll see
about that later. דבר *Davar*, so כי יפלא ממך דבר *ki yippalei
mimcha davar*. I lost my place right off the פסוק pasuk *passuk*.
After my gorgeous drawing here of the בית המקדש beit hamikdash *Beit
Hamikdash*. Okay. כי יפלא ממך דבר למשפט בין דם לדם Bein dam
ledam, בין דין לדין bein din l'din, בין נגע לנגע bein nega
l'nega דברי ריבות divrei rivot? בשעריך bishe'arecha, *Ki yippalei mimcha davar
lamishpat
bein dam l'dam bein din l'din bein nega
l'nega divrei rivot b'sha'arecha*. Okay. Each one of these is going to
tell us something about the type of the דין din *din* that
they could be debating. So יפלא *yippalei* tells us that that's a
מומחה *mumcheh*, okay. ממך *mimcha* somehow tells us יועץ *yoetz* which sounds
like it's a personal characteristic but somehow we're going to say that
it's going to mean that it's talking about קידוש החודש Kiddush Hachodesh
*Kiddush Hachodesh*. Okay. דבר זו הלכה halacha *Davar zo halacha*. So דבר
*davar* means a הלכה halacha *halacha*, a הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha le-Moshe
mi-Sinai. *Halacha L'Moshe MiSinai*, presumably because it was just an oral tradition.
Okay, so that's הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha le-Moshe mi-Sinai *Halacha L'Moshe MiSinai*.
דבר *Davar* means even if they're debating an oral tradition. למשפט זה
הדין *Lamishpat zeh hadin*. So somehow משפט *mishpat*, it's going to say
בין דין לדין *bein din l'din* here. So this למשפט *lamishpat* somehow
רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says based on the later גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, דין
*din* here means a גזירה שוה gezeirah shavah. *gezeirah shavah*. Don't ask
me how משפט *mishpat* means judgment and judgment means גזירה שוה gezeirah
shavah. *gezeirah shavah*. I have no idea. But anyway, but it's interesting,
right? הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha LeMoshe MiSinai. *Halacha L'Moshe MiSinai* means we're
not just debating how to read a פסוק pasuk, *passuk*, we're debating
what the tradition is. גזירה שוה gezeirah shavahs *Gezeirah shavah* is we're
we're debating some of the hermeneutics of how to read the פסוקים
psukim *pessukim*. Okay. בין דם לדם בין דם נדה Niddah לדם לידה
leidah ודם זיבה *Bein dam l'dam bein dam niddah l'dam leidah v'dam
zivah*. Okay, so דם לדם *dam l'dam* is some debate about bloods
that are טמא Tamei. *tamei*. נדה Niddah. *Niddah*, לידה *leidah*, and זיבה
*zivah*. Okay, we'll have to see about that. Okay. Okay, בין דין
לדין בין דיני נפשות dinei nefashos דיני ממונות dinei mamonus, דיני מכות
*Bein din l'din bein dinei nefashot dinei mamonot dinei makkot*. So this
is all the different types of judgments that could be passed against
somebody. Okay, נפשות *nefashot*, מכות *makkot*, and oh, ממונות mamonus *mamonot*.
Okay, because this is ritual, right? So here these are these are
the types of derivations, הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha LeMoshe MiSinai *Halacha L'Moshe
MiSinai*, גזירה שוה gezeirah shavah *gezeirah shavah*. These are ritual, this is
sort of interpersonal, right? Well, I guess punishing somebody could also be
a punishment and a crime, not interpersonal. But anyway, okay, but this
is purely ritual. This is more like punishment oriented. Okay. בין נגע
לנגע בין נגעי אדם nig'ei adam נגעי בתים nigei batim, נגעי בגדים
nigei bgadim,
*Bein nega l'nega bein nig'ei adam nig'ei batim nig'ei bgadim*. So that's
reading God's and smitings which is probably the פשט pshat *pshat*, but
נגוע *negua* like צרעת tzara'as *tzara'at*. Okay. So that's back to certain
like purely ritual ideas. I'm not sure exactly what the חידוש *chiddush*
is. I mean if it applies to question if somebody is a
נדה Niddah. *niddah*, applies question if somebody is a מצורע metzora *metzora*,
it's טומאה tumah. וטהרה *tumah v'taharah*, it's a ritual point. דברי *Divrei*,
words, אלו חרמים וערכין והקדשות *elu charamim v'arachin v'hekdeshot*.
So this דברי *divrei*, this דבר *davar* meant it was an oral
tradition. This דברי *divrei* means that it's a type of a verbal
act which is הפלאה *hafla'ah*, right? That's what יפלא *yippalei* means. Okay,
which is basically like so if you make something you're מקדיש *makdish*,
you חרם *cherem*, you know you make a vow, you make whatever,
so it's issues relating to those verbal acts. Okay, ריבות *rivot*,
dispute, זו השקאת סוטה sotah *zo hashk'at sotah*, having the סוטה *sotah*
drink the water because like you know... her husband are having a
dispute, right? That's more identified as a dispute than like monetary disputes,
I don't know, okay. Anyway,
ועריפת עגלה, the breaking of the neck of the calf, when somebody
got murdered, a murder victim. Again, why is that דברי ריבות? Okay,
so רש"י Rashi says, you know, often people get murdered because of
a fight, but still, why, what specifically? So the things that סוטה
and עריפת עגלה ערופה arifat eglah arufa have in common is that
it's a type of a ritual done when you don't know what
happened exactly. So maybe part of the thing here is not just
that they're fighting, but that somehow it's indeterminate, you know, it remains
a fight. Okay, one minute, וטהרת מצורע. ve-taharat metzora. Now what a
מצורע metzora has to do with this is unclear. רש"י Rashi says,
well, you know, מצורע metzora comes because of like לשון הרע, lashon
hara, because of also because of speech acts. It's again a little
unclear what that whole collection is. בשעריך, bishe'arecha זו לקט שכחה ופאה.
zu leket shikcha u'peah. Okay, because since it says you give these
gifts to the poor in your gates, so the בשעריך is coming
to speak about gifts to the poor. So that's somewhat in between
the idea of like fighting on monetary disputes and purely ritual. It's
a מצוה mitzvah of giving to the poor. וקמת, ve-kamta, so that's
the whole range of things, מבית דין. mi-beit din. So you go
from your בית דין beit din where you're debating it, ועלית, ve-alita,
and you go to the בית דין Beis Din that's in ירושלים.
yerushalayim. מלמד שבית המקדש גבוה מארץ ישראל. melamed she-beit hamikdash gavo'ah mi-eretz
yisrael.
So the fact that it uses the words go up means that
the בית המקדש beit hamikdash is the highest point in the land
of Israel. Now we don't necessarily mean this literally. תוספות tosafot says
that there's actually mountains that are higher, maybe with the walls the
בית המקדש beit hamikdash is higher. Obviously we also mean it spiritually.
Now that we're saying that the בית המקדש beit hamikdash is the
highest point in Israel, we also say ארץ ישראל גבוהה מכל הארצות.
eretz yisrael gevoha mi-kol ha-aratzot. Israel is the highest land of all
of the lands. Also presumably we mean this spiritually. Okay, that's a
parenthetical. So you shall go אל המקום el hamakom to the one
place that God has chosen means to הר הבית. har habayit. מלמד
שהמקום גורם. melamed she-hamakom gorem.
It has to be exactly in that place. If he disputes the
court but they're not actually sitting in the בית המקדש beit hamikdash
on הר הבית, har habayit, he doesn't become a זקן ממרא. zaken
mamre That's the end of the ברייתא. braita. Okay, now the גמרא
Gemara is going to unpack this ברייתא. braita. I can't take questions.
בשלמא בית המקדש גבוה מארץ ישראל דכתיב ועלית. bishlama beit hamikdash gavo'ah
mi-eretz yisrael de-chtiv ve-alita.
So that's in the פסוק pasuk that the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash
is implicitly the highest place. אלא ארץ ישראל גבוהה מכל הארצות מנלן?
ela eretz yisrael gevoha mi-kol ha-aratzot minalan? How do you know Israel
is higher than all other lands? דכתיב לכן הנה ימים באים נאם
ה', de-chtiv lachen hinei yamim ba'im neum hashem, days will come, ולא
יאמרו עוד חי ה' אשר העלה את בני ישראל מארץ מצרים, velo
yomru od chai hashem asher he'ela et benei yisrael me'eretz mitzrayim, praise
God who took the בני ישראל benei yisrael who raised בני ישראל
benei yisrael out of the land of Egypt, כי אם חי ה'
אשר העלה ואשר הביא את זרע בית ישראל מארץ צפונה ומכל הארצות
אשר הדחתים שם וישבו על אדמתם, ki im chai hashem asher he'ela
va'asher hevi et zera beit yisrael me'eretz tzafona u'mikol ha'aratzot asher hidachtim
sham ve-yashvu al admatam, that he brought them from all the lands
and they will dwell in their land. Anyway, the point being that
the word it uses to bring them from other lands to Israel
is העלה, he'ela, to raise up, like make עליה. aliyah. Okay, so
the fact that it uses that verb shows again whether literally or
figuratively ארץ ישראל eretz yisrael is the highest of all lands. Okay,
that was a very side point. תנו רבנן. tanu rabanan. Now we
have this list of all these different types of derivations and laws,
but now we're going to have a debate, what types of laws
are they debating and how are they debating it? זקן ממרא אינו
חייב אלא על דבר שזדונו כרת ושגגתו חטאת דברי רבי מאיר. zaken
mamre eino chayav ela al davar she-zedono karet u'shegagato chatat divrei rabbi
meir. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says a זקן ממרא zaken mamre is
only for something that were somebody to listen to him and do
it, it would lead to the bringing of a קרבן חטאת korban
chatat if he did it בשוגג, be-shogeg, or if he did it
במזיד be-mezid it would lead to כרת. karet. Now obviously what he's
using is he's using the model of a normal קרבן חטאת, korban
chatat, right? A normal sort of weighty sin, right? Is and if
you think about it, right? There's other people that have special statuses
when they give פסק. psak. If a בית דין Beis Din. rules
incorrectly, the בית דין הגדול beit din ha-gadol and people listen to
them, they bring the פר העלם דבר של ציבור. par he'elem davar
shel tzibur. If a כהן גדול kohen gadol rules and he acts
on his own ruling, it's a weird הלכה halacha by כהן גדול,
kohen gadol, he brings a special קרבן. korban. So here זקן ממרא
zaken mamre. is ruling. What do we have special statuses of ruling
by קרבנות? korbanot? And for them it's the classic type of a
sin that you bring a קרבן korban for, which is a sin
that's deserving of כרת karet and בשוגג be-shogeg a חטאת. chatat. So
here even though what he's doing is במזיד, be-mezid, not בשוגג, be-shogeg,
and his real problem is undermining their authority, yes, ultimately he's telling
people to act, but the real problem is not that he's being
מכשיל machshil a million people to sin, right? Even if nobody listens
to him, he just tells people to act, he's a זקן ממרא.
Zaken Mamre. Nevertheless we're reading it through that lens and saying the
type of case he's ruling on is one of these weighty cases
which if it were done בשוגג be-shogeg would be a חטאת chatat
and if it were done במזיד be-mezid would be חייב כרת. chayav
karet. So that's רבי מאיר's Rabbi Meir position. Number one, it has
to be a weighty type of a sin. רבי יהודה אומר על
דבר שעיקרו מדברי תורה ופירושו מדברי סופרים. rabbi yehuda omer al davar
she-ikaro mi-divrei torah u'perusho mi-divrei soferim. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda doesn't care
about how weighty the sin is, he cares about the nature of
the dispute, what type of an authority is being, are they quoting,
or what type of a פסק. psak. is being given, and he
says he has to be ruling on something which is based in
a פסוק pasuk... *pasuk* in the תורה Torah, *Torah*, but is interpreted
through Rabbinic interpretation. Right, because if he basically, let's say argues on,
like here we threw in a הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha LeMoshe MiSinai,
*Halacha L'Moshe MiSinai*. A הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha LeMoshe MiSinai *Halacha L'Moshe
MiSinai* isn't based on a פסוק pasuk *pasuk*. He just says, that's
your tradition, I have a different tradition. Right, so or let's say
he just rules directly against the פסוק pasuk *pasuk*. He says the
תורה Torah, *Torah* says you're supposed to keep שבת *Shabbos*, I don't
think you're supposed to keep שבת *Shabbos*, right? So those types of
things, it's like the classic act of the בית דין הגדול Beis
Din haGadol *Beit Din HaGadol* is to, like if you think about
the Supreme Court, their classic role is to interpret the, the you
know, the Constitution. The classic authority of the בית דין הגדול Beis
Din haGadol *Beit Din HaGadol* is to interpret the פסוקים psukim, *psukim*
in the תורה Torah. *Torah*. And therefore, if he's just ruling something
that is against פסוקים psukim, *psukim* in the תורה Torah *Torah* or
against a tradition, but it's not arguing with this authority of how
to interpret פסוקים psukim. *psukim*, then he's not really seen—he might be
מכשיל *machshil* people—but he's not really seen as putting himself up as
a competing authority or as undermining their authority, because their primary authority
is defined in the sense that the תורה Torah *Torah* says you
don't know what the תורה Torah. *Torah* means, you go to them,
they'll tell you על פי התורה אשר יורוך yoru-cha, *Al Pi HaTorah
Asher Yorucha*, which means presumably like their teaching that they teach you,
but of course the way it's understood is based on the way
they understand the פסוקים *psukim*, that is the law that you have
to follow. So it's only when he does that type of a
mode of interpreting פסוקים *psukim* is he seen as really competing with
their authority. Yeah. So רבי Rabbi ישמעאל *Rabbi Yishmael* and רבי עקיבא
*Rabbi Akiva* famously have different approaches. Right. If there was a בית
דין הגדול Beis Din Hagadol *Beit Din HaGadol* and they decided one
way and they had ruled another way and they told people to
listen to them, they'd be a זקן ממרא Zaken Mamre. *Zaken Mamre*.
Okay, obviously there are disputes about all these things. The problem isn't
that you're disputing it, the problem is when the final court has
ruled, you continue to rule in opposition and tell people to listen
to you. Okay, but you have to be ruling in a way
that you're competing with their authority. Okay, if you're just telling people
to sin, then fine, you're a מכשיל *machshil*, okay, but you're not
a זקן ממרא Zaken Mamre *Zaken Mamre*. I'm serious. The problem is
not that people are listening—the problem is that you are taking on
the role that they have in defiance of the fact that they
have given their final ruling on this case. Okay, so רבי יהודה'ס
*Rabbi Yehuda's* position makes a lot of sense, although it doesn't seem
to exactly fit the הלכה halacha. למשה מסיני *Halacha L'Moshe MiSinai* part
of this ברייתא braisa *braita*. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon, אומר אפילו דקדוק
אחד dikduk echad. מדקדוקי סופרים *Rabbi Shimon Omer afilu dikduk echad m'dikdukei
sofrim*, even if it's one little jot or tittle of the what
the סופרים *sofrim* say. Now what does he mean? דקדוקי סופרים *Dikdukei
sofrim* is always a vague term. Does that mean a Rabbinic ruling,
if he disagrees with some ruling about פורים Purim? *Purim* or חנוכה
*Chanukah* or נטילת ידיים *Netilat Yadayim*, he's a זקן ממרא Zaken Mamre
*Zaken Mamre*? Or does דקדוקי סופרים *dikdukei sofrim* mean like a, you
know, again, their role of interpreting the תורה Torah *Torah*? It might
be a tiny little point, but it's still in the context of
them interpreting the תורה Torah, *Torah*. If so, it's not clear how
he disagrees, right, with רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda*. So what
exactly רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon *Rabbi Shimon* is saying, how
broad is דקדוקי סופרים *dikdukei sofrim* is not exactly clear. We'll have
to see about all of this. But the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* starts
with רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir. *Rabbi Meir*. Okay, today's דף daf. *daf*
is going to be devoted to רבי מאיר'ס *Rabbi Meir's* position. Now,
מאי טעמיה דרבי מאיר *mai ta'amei d'Rabbi Meir*? What's the reason of
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rabbi Meir* that says it has to be
a sin that's deserving of a חטאת chatas *chatas* or כרת kareis
*kares*? גמר דבר דבר *Gmar davar davar*, it's a גזירה שוה gezeirah
shavah. *gezeirah shava*. כתיב הכא כי יפלא ממך דבר *K'siv hacha ki
yipalei mimcha davar*, a matter, למשפט *l'mishpat*. Now what is a matter?
וכתיב התם ונעלם דבר מעיני הקהל *U'chsiv hatam v'ne'elam davar m'einei hakahal*,
like I said, it's not just a גזירה שוה gezeirah shavah *gezeirah
shava*, there you're dealing with the בית דין Beis Din. הגדול *Beit
Din HaGadol* bringing a קרבן *korban* for their הוראה hora'ah, *hora'ah* and
for people listening to them. Now there actually רוב *rov* of כלל
ישראל *K'lal Yisrael* have to listen to them and there really was
that their הוראה *hora'ah* was מכשיל *machshil* people. But it's a הוראה
*hora'ah* about something that you're חייב חטאת chayav chattas, *chayav chatas*. So
therefore since this is about him being, giving authority and ruling, being
מורה *moreh*, it's in the same context as their
הוראה *hora'ah* which leads to a קרבן *korban*, which is a הוראה
*hora'ah* about something that you're חייב חטאת chattas, *chayav chatas*. מה להלן
דבר שחייב על זדונו כרת ועל שגגתו חטאת chattas, *Ma halan davar
she'chayav al z'dono kares v'al shigagato chatas*, the same way there it's
a type of a sin that you get כרת *kares* if you
are willful and חטאת chattas. *chatas* if you're unintentional, and that's when
for their הוראה *hora'ah* they would bring a קרבן *korban*, so אף
כאן af kan *af kan*, here when he gives a הוראה *hora'ah*
and he's doing it willingly and he's undermining etc. their authority and
all of that, nevertheless, it's the same type of a weighty issue.
על דבר שחייב כרת אף כאן דבר שחייב על זדונו כרת ועל
שגגתו חטאת *Al davar she'chayav kares af kan davar she'chayav al z'dono
kares v'al shigagato chatas*. Okay. רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda*, now רבי יהודה
*Rabbi Yehuda* says you don't need it to be that weighty. What
would his response be? על פי התורה אשר יורוך *Al pi haTorah
asher yorucha*. It says, no, by the תורה Torah, *Torah* they teach
you, אד דאיכא *ad deika*—I'm sorry, they're not addressing why it doesn't
have to be that weighty. He just doesn't דרשן *darshen* that. Fine.
He doesn't need it to be something you're חייב חטאת *chayav chatas*.
How does he know it has to be something that's based on
an interpretation of a פסוק *pasuk*? So he says because it says
על פי *Al pi*... על פי התורה אשר יורוך. עד איכא Ad
ika תורה, Torah, it's based on a פסוק in the תורה, ויורוך,
ve-yoru-cha, and then based on an interpretation of that פסוק, a ruling
based on a פסוק in the תורה. Okay, so that's how he
reads it. Again, the פשט pshat of the פסוק... I can't take
questions... the פשט of the פסוק is תורה is יורוך, is הוראה,
is a ruling. So the literal meaning of the פסוק is based
on the ruling that they rule for you. Okay, but he's reading
תורה in the sense of פסוקים in the תורה. Okay, so based
on the scripture is the way he's reading it, not the ruling.
The scripture that they interpret for you. So the classic role, as
I said, of the בית דין Beis Din. הגדול is to interpret
the scripture. What, you know, what is the meaning of the פסוקים,
of the מצוות? mitzvos? And therefore, only when he takes that competing
role does he become a זקן ממרא. Zaken Mamre רבי שמעון, Rabbi
Shimon now רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon, says even a דקדוק אחד. So
what would that mean? אשר יגידו לך מן המקום ההוא. Asher yagidu
lecha min hamakom hahu. What they tell you from that place. אפילו
כל דהו. Afilu kol dehu. Even the smallest thing that they tell
you, if you disagree, you have to follow them. So again, really
to an extreme, he means that this applies even to דרבננ'ס, DeRabbanan's,
right? Which is funny, because we normally assume that the primary point
here is that you are putting yourself up as a competing, sort
of interpretive authority, right? As a competing authority of who gets to
interpret what the תורה means. But if they're talking about like a
דרבנן, DeRabbanan, what do you have to do for, what order do
you light נרות חנוכה? neiros Chanukah? So then he's putting himself as
a competing legislative authority. It's a very different type of a dispute.
Unless you could make a point like, no, no, no, they're not
saying that they rule this is how you light נרות חנוכה, neiros
Chanukah, whatever, like it's about who legislated. It's a question like what
always has been the practice for this דרבנן? DeRabbanan? It's still interpretive,
but we're not interpreting the תורה, we're not interpreting scripture, we're interpreting
previous rabbinic rulings, right? You understand how that could, right? How that
could be, right? Like, okay, we all know that an earlier חז"ל
ruled about מוקצה. muktzah. And now we're having debates what are the
scope of מוקצה. muktzah. So we're not having a debate about how
to legislate, we're having a debate about how to interpret an earlier
ruling of the rabbis. Okay, so that would be much more comfortable,
that it's still a question about who has the, sort of, you
know, who has this authority to give the binding interpretation. We're not
dealing with the question of legislation. We're dealing with the role of
interpretation, right? But there he's saying, but it doesn't have to be
interpreting God's word. It's any role of playing a role of being
an interpreter of הלכה Halacha can make you a זקן ממרא. Zaken
Mamre Okay, that seems to be the point. But again, it's not
clear. Maybe he would say it would even be a broader scope.
It is not clear how far רבי שמעון Shimon goes. Okay, so
now we... so that's the... those are the opinions. One about the
weightiness of it, and the other two, רבי יהודה and רבי שמעון,
Shimon's about what... which I think is much more interesting... is what
type of authority and what type of a role, you know, is
the זקן ממרא Zaken Mamre sort of doing in terms of saying,
"I am the authority to do what?" right? To interpret the פסוקים,
to give any rulings, to interpret, you know, to be an interpreter
of any law, and so on. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara
says like this. אמר ליה רב הונא בר חיננא לרבא, Amar lei
Rav Huna bar Chinana le-Rava, תרגמה לי להא מתניתין, targema li le-ha
masnisin,
explain to me this whole ברייתא braisa that gave, interpreted all of
these cases, okay, אליבא דרבי מאיר. aliba de-Rabbi Meir. Explain to me
how this all works according to רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir, רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir. says it has to be something you're חייב כרת chayav
kares for. How does all of these cases that we listed in
this ברייתא Braita, lead to a חיוב כרת? chiyuv kares? Now, that's
ostensibly the question, but what we're going to do is we're going
to go through and we're sort of going to not connect the
dots between what we're about to say and how it leads to
a חיוב כרת. chiyuv kares. Like, רש"י Rashi connects the dots. The
גמרא is not going to connect the dots. What we're really going
to do, under the... under the sort of auspices of saying how
this works with רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir. is go through each of
these and explain how any one of these things could be a
matter of debate. And it's really quite beautiful, it's sort of like
what Charlie said before, what the גמרא does. Because the problem here
is not that there are going to be debates. There's always debates.
The problem is that you kept on פסק'ינג paskening the way you
did after the final arbiter, the final court gave its ruling. So
we're going to go through each one of these and show how
there's debates about every single thing here. There are תנאי'יק Tannaic debates
about the scope of every single thing mentioned in the... in these
פסוקים. So that one could imagine that the זקן ממרא Zaken Mamre,
and the בית דין beis din הגדול are just having a classic
debate of תנאים Tannaim about is this the הלכה halacha or that
the הלכה. The problem is not that the זקן ממרא zaken mamre
is saying something, you know, offensive. He might actually be right. The
problem isn't even that he's saying something wrong. Okay? The problem is
that he's keep ruling after בית דין beis din has ruled. So
we're going to go through all of these and show that every
single one of these has areas that the תנאים Tannaim debate. And
that could be the debate between who has the, sort of, you
know... זקן ממרא Zaken Mamre and the בית דין. beis din Okay,
so let's take a look. Okay. אמר ליה רבא לרב פפא פוק
תרגמה ליה. Amar lei Rava le-Rav Papa puk targema lei. So רבא
Rava said to רב פפא, Rav Papa, oh
you know, whatever, this רב הונא Rav Huna wants to know how
this all works according to רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir, Go explain to
him how all these cases work for רבי מאיר. Okay. כי פליגי
במופלא שבבית דין קא משמע לן. Ki palei be-mufla she-be-Beis Din ka-mashma
lan. Okay, so that's not relevant. That just says the guy has
to, can't be a תלמיד, has to be on the בית דין.
beis din מנחה זה יועץ ונבון לחש. Mincha ze yoetz ve-navon lachash.
Now what's that, what's the whole point of that line? שיודע לעבר
שנים ולקבוע חדשים. She-yodea le-aber shanim ve-likboa chadashim.
So this wasn't clear in the ברייתא, I mentioned this to you.
It means that the person has to be able to give a
פסק Psak about, about קידוש החודש and עיבור שנה. Ibur Shana. So
you could say that's just a personal qualification of what type of
an authority we're dealing with. But the גמרא now translates it into
the idea that they could be debating a question about קידוש החודש.
What would an example of that be? דתנן הני עדי שמעברין את
השנה כל אדר. Ditnan heni eidi she-m'abrin es ha-shana kol Adar.
So these two תנאים, Tannaim, whatever, came and testified that you could
make the, add an extra month even to the last day of
אדר. Adar. You know, you could make it עיבור שנה. Ibur Shana.
שהיו אומרים
עד הפורים, She-hayu omrim ad ha-Purim, because before them the tradition was
עד הפורים. ad ha-Purim. So maybe that was a debate of the
זקן ממרא and the בית דין. beis din Could you make, add
an extra month after פורים? Now, okay, so that's one area of
debate. Now how does that lead to something that you're חייב כרת
chayav Kares for? How could that lead to it? Clearly, because if
you're debating whether you added a month or not, you're debating when
פסח Pesach is. So if you're debating when פסח Pesach is, you're
debating whether you're חייב כרת chayav Kares for eating חמץ Chametz or
not. According if you listen to the זקן ממרא, you'll eat חמץ
Chametz on a day that, you know, he says isn't פסח, Pesach,
but the בית דין beis din הגדול says is פסח, Pesach, and
you'll be חייב כרת. chayav Kares. דאי להאי גיסא קא שרי חמץ
בפסח ואי להאי גיסא קא שרי חמץ בפסח. De-i le-hai gisa ka
sharei chametz be-pesach ve-i le-hai gisa ka sharei chametz be-pesach.
Whichever one you listen to, if you add the month, if you
do add the month or you don't add the month, then one
of those months you're going to be eating חמץ Chametz according to
the other position, right? You get how that works, right? So therefore,
that's a way they could be debating a קידוש החודש and it
could be a type of a חיוב כרת. chiyuv Kares. So we're
both getting a concrete example what they could be debating about and
how this is a debate that exists in the תנאים Tannaim and
how it could lead to a חיוב כרת. chiyuv Kares. We're going
to sort of drop the connecting the dots to the חיוב כרת
chiyuv Kares very quickly. Okay. So now we have like this. דבר
שהוא הלכה, Davar she-hu halacha, that's the הלכה למשה מסיני. So what
could they be debating? They could be debating זו הלכתא דאחד עשר.
zu hilchata de-achad asar. The הלכה of the הלכה למשה מסיני of
the eleven days. You know, eleven days are when a woman gets
her period, she's a נדה Niddah, for seven days. Okay, and then
she, according to the תורה, she would go to the מקוה Mikvah
the night of the seventh day from the onset of bleeding. And
then would follow, so from day eight from the onset of her
period for eleven days till day nineteen would be the eleven days
that she could become a זבה. Zava. That if she bled three
days in a row during those eleven days, she would be a
זבה. Zava. If she, if she bled on day nineteen, then she
would become
a, no, from day eight till eighteen she could be a זבה.
Zava. If she bled on day nineteen she would be a נדה.
niddah. But if she bled three days in a row during those
eleven days, she'd be a זבה. Zava. Now, to be a זבה
Zava according to the תורה, a woman needs to bleed three days
in a row. Okay, and if she bleeds, so here are the
eleven days, right, one, two, three, whatever, eleven, ten, nine, okay. Now
if a woman were to bleed on days, you know, I don't
know, three, four, and five, she would be a זבה. Zava. And
then she would need seven days without blood to become טהור. Tahor.
If she only bled on day three, she would just, she would
make sure that day four was clean and then she'd be okay.
Okay, but until day four is clean, she's still טמא. tamei If
she bled on two days, three and four, she'd make sure day
five is, has no blood, and then she would be טהור. Tahor.
Okay, so she would need one clean day if she had one
or two days of bleeding. If she has three days of bleeding,
she needs seven clean days. Fine. What happens if she, now the
last opportunity she could have to become a full זבה Zava and
require seven clean days is if she bleeds on days nine, ten,
and eleven. So if she bleeds on days nine and ten, she
has to make sure she's not bleeding on day eleven or else
she'll become a זבה. Zava. But what if she bleeds on day
eleven? If she bleeds on day eleven there is no way, what
would happen if she bled on the next day? She'd be a
נדה. There is no way she will become a זבה, Zava, a
full זבה Zava of three days. So therefore she bleeds on day
eleven, she does not need to wait a clean day before going
to the מקוה, Mikvah, because there's no way it could, she could
become a זבה. Zava. What if she bled on day ten? So
on the one hand, if she bled on day ten, there's no
way she could become a זבה Zava because if she bleeds three
days, she's a נדה, not a זבה. Zava. So you might say
you don't need a clean day in this case and she automatically
just goes to the מקוה. Mikvah. But you could say, but the
fact that day eleven is still in the זבה Zava period, so
maybe even though she can't become a full זבה, Zava, she still
needs day eleven as a clean day. If she bled on day
eleven, then... It would be crazy to say she needs a נידה
Niddah day to make her to deal with the זבה Zavah problem.
But she bled on day 10, maybe she would require a clean
day, and that's the debate about day 11. Okay? I hope you
got all of that. Okay.
So it says like this. Okay. זו
אחת עשר. Zu achat asar. דאיתמר. De'itmar. עשירי. Asiri. What happens if
she bleeds on day 10? רבי יוחנן אמר עשירי כתשיעי. Rabbi Yochanan
amar: Asiri keteshi'i. It's like day 9, so she needs a clean
day before she can go to the מקוה. Mikvah. וריש לקיש אמר
עשירי כאחת עשר. VeResh Lakish amar: Asiri ke'achat asar. She doesn't need
it's like day 11, she doesn't need a clean day. רבי יוחנן
אמר עשירי כתשיעי מה תשיעי בעי שימור, Rabbi Yochanan amar: Asiri keteshi'i,
ma teshi'i ba'i shimur, the same way day 9 needs a clean
day before she can go to the מקוה, Mikvah, אף עשירי בעי
שימור. af asiri ba'i shimur. The same is true about day 10.
וריש לקיש אמר עשירי כאחת עשר מה אחת עשר לא בעי שימור,
VeResh Lakish amar: Asiri ke'achat asar, ma achat asar lo ba'i shimur,
the same way 11 doesn't need a clean day, אף עשירי לא
בעי שימור. af asiri lo ba'i shimur. It doesn't. So that's how
they're debating the scope of a הלכה למשה מסיני. Now whether הלכה
למשה מסיני exists, this whole idea of 11 days is הלכה למשה
מסיני, but the exact parameters of it. Now notice we are not
bothering to spell out how this is חייב כרת chayav kares or
not. But it's obvious, right? If she's, you know, if she thinks
she's clean, she doesn't need a clean day and she goes to
the מקוה Mikvah and she's still a זבה, Zavah, right? And then
she has sex with her husband, then that's a חייב כרת. chayav
kares. Okay. So whether she can go to the מקוה Mikvah with
or without a clean day has clear implications for an issue of
חייב כרת. chayav kares. Okay. So we've got how ראש חודש Rosh
Chodesh has implications for חייב כרת chayav kares and how הלכה למשה
מסיני does.
Okay. משפט זה הדין. Mishpat zeh hadin. So דין בתו מאנוסתו. din
bito me'anusato. So this is again דין here is interpreted as גזירה
שוה. gezeirah shavah. So this is the question, you remember, about whether
a man's daughter who is not his wife's daughter the גמרא just
describes it as the daughter of the woman he raped, doesn't have
to have raped a woman, his daughter that's not his wife's
daughter, a woman he never married, okay how do we know that
it's אסור assur for him to have intercourse with her? We know
that he can't have intercourse with his grand whatever, you know, granddaughter,
whatever, anyway, it's never clear that he can't have intercourse with this
explicitly. So דאמר רבא de'amar Rava and רבא Rava says you learn
it from a גזירה gezeirah. שוה. דאמר רבא אמר ליה רב יצחק
בר אבדימי, De'amar Rava amar lei Rav Yitzchak bar Avdimi, אתיא הנה
הנה אתיא זימה זימה. atya henah henah, atya zimah zimah. We make
two double גזירה שוה to teach you that it's prohibited a man
having intercourse with his daughter who is not his wife's daughter. Okay.
Now we did that. Now so therefore that's a case of גזירה
שוה which clearly it would be worse than a חייב כרת. chayav
kares. חייב כרת chayav kares is חייב כרת chayav kares or worse.
So something that is a
חייב מיתה, chayav misah, okay, clearly is in the חייב כרת chayav
kares category. Now תוספות Tosafot points out of all the things we're
going to go through, this is the only one that's not a
matter of dispute. Okay. But nevertheless you could imagine that a זקן
ממרא would say, I don't agree with that גזירה שוה. I don't
think it's אסור assur for a man to have intercourse with his
daughter, okay, if it's not his wife's daughter. So that would be
an area of disputing something that is based on a גזירה שוה
that is has that weightiness. It's funny though, you could imagine a
million issues that are based on a גזירה שוה. Why the גמרא
picked this one? Probably because we've been dealing with it already. Okay,
let's keep on going. You could even be creative enough to refute
the גזירה. Exactly. Okay. בין דם לדם, okay, בין דם נידה דם
לידה דם זיבה. bein dam niddah, dam leidah, dam zivah. Okay. So
what are their debates in those
areas? דם נידה בפלוגתא דעקביא בן מהללאל ורבנן. Dam niddah biflugta de'Akavya
ben Mehalalel veRabbanan. Okay, that debate. דנן. Denan. So again, we're just
going through areas with תנאים Tannaim debate because the problem isn't that
what he's saying is a bad idea or even wrong. The problem
is just that he's continuing to say it after he's been overruled.
Okay, דנן, denan, so where's the debate by נידה? niddah? דם הירוק,
Dam hayarok, if the blood is green or ירוק yarok might mean
yellowish, עקביא בן מהללאל מטמא, Akavya ben Mehalalel metamei, he says that
that type of a color is דם נידה, dam niddah, וחכמים מטהרין,
vachachamim metaharin, the Rabbis say it's not. So they could be debating
is this woman a נידה niddah or not with implications, she's going
to go have sex with her husband and that's a חייב כרת
chayav kares type of an implication. Okay, so that's an area, clear
simple area that they could debate which is a חייב כרת. chayav
kares. Okay.
דם לידה בפלוגתא דרב ולוי. Dam leidah biflugta deRav veLevi. The לידה
debate is the רב Rav and לוי, Levi, it could be the
רב Rav and לוי Levi debate. דאיתמר, De'itmar, רב אמר מעיין אחד
הוא, Rav amar: Ma'ayan echad hu, it's one wellspring. התורה טימאתו והתורה
טיהרתו. Hatorah tim'ato vehatorah tiharato. The Torah said it's tamei, the Torah
said it's tahor. What does that mean? It means that the הלכה
is, Torah says if a woman has a baby boy, she's טמא
tamei for seven days, just double all this for a girl, okay,
so she's טמא tamei, for seven days, she's טמא, tamei. and then
afterwards she's דם טוהר. dam tohar. Even if she bleeds, it does
not make her טמא. tamei, That is from day 8 through day
40, right? People know that? Okay, and then you just double it
for a girl, it's 14 and through day 80. And then starting
on day 41, if she bleeds she will be
טמא, tamei okay, if she bleeds. Here she's automatically טמא tamei as
soon as she's given birth. and here even if she bleeds she
is טהור. tahor. So the question is, why is she טהור tahor
if she bleeds during this period? Is it that we assume that
it's no longer it's not it's not uterine bleeding, the source of
the blood is a different source of blood that שתי מעיינות shtei
ma'ayanot there are two wellsprings. We imagine blood like coming forth from
a wellspring as it were in the woman. So the blood that
is טמא tamei, comes from one source in the woman, blood that
is טהור tahor comes from another, and then on day 41 it
shifts back to the other source. So basically it's saying this isn't
uterine blood, it's coming from somewhere else. That's one explanation. The other
explanation is no, מעיין אחד, ma'ayan echad, it's all uterine blood, it's
all coming from the same place. But the Torah has told us
that for this period of time she's going to be טהור. tahor.
התורה
טימאה והתורה טיהרה. ha-Torah tim'ah ve-ha-Torah tihara. Good, it's uterine blood, but
during this period of time she's טהור tahor because, you know, it's
all based on the birth act anyway. So who cares? Like if
either way we agree to this, what's the נפקא מינא? nafka mina?
So the Gemara says the נפקא מינא nafka mina is that she's
bleeding without a break between from day seven to day eight. Okay,
she's bleeding, you know, from right before שקיעה shkiyah on day seven
to right after שקיעה shkiyah on day eight. If it's two different
sources, we would not say in this case it's two different sources.
We'd say the evidence clearly shows it's coming from the same source.
So even though she's bleeding on day eight, we would say that
she was טמא, tamei okay? Or if she was bleeding from day
40 to 41. If the logic is it's two different sources, then
here we would say the bleeding on day 41 is that it's
טהור tahor because it's coming from the same source, it was a
continuous bleeding. But if the point is that the Torah just changed
its status, it wouldn't matter that it's a continuous bleeding. Once it's
in this period of time, the status changes. Once it's in this
period of time, the status changes. Okay, so that's the debate about
דם לידה. dam leidah. Okay, and ורב אמר מעיין אחד הוא התורה
טימאה והתורה טיהרה ולוי אמר שתי מעיינות הן. ve-Rav amar ma'ayan echad
hu ha-Torah tim'ah ve-ha-Torah tihara ve-Levi amar shtei ma'ayanot hen. So if
Rav says מעיין אחד הוא, ma'ayan echad hu, התורה טימאה והתורה טיהרה,
ha-Torah tim'ah ve-ha-Torah tihara, ולוי אמר שתי מעיינות הן, ve-Levi amar shtei
ma'ayanot hen, there are two wellsprings, נסתם הטמא נפתח הטהור, nistam ha-tamei
niftach ha-tahor, the טמא tamei one closes and the טהור tahor one
opens up. And then at the end of day 40 days, נסתם
הטהור ונפתח הטמא, nistam ha-tahor ve-niftach ha-tamei, the טהור tahor one closes,
the טמא tamei, one opens up, and with the נפקא מינא nafka
minas that we said. So if they're debating this, it's a debate
with implications of is she טמא, tamei. is she טהור, tahor, and
therefore with implications about a חייב כרת chayav kares type of a
scenario. Okay, everybody get that? Alright. Now, דם זיבה, dam zivah, what's
the debate about a זבה? zavah? בפלוגתא
דרבי אליעזר ורבי יהושע דתנן, biphlogta de-Rabbi Eliezer ve-Rabbi Yehoshua ditnan, הישתה
שלושה ימים. hishtah shlosha yamim. This is a nice little distillation of
like the most obscure aspects of הלכות נדה. hilchos niddah. Okay, הישתה
שלושה ימים בתוך אחד עשר יום. hishtah shlosha yamim betoch achad asar
yom. If a woman, if a woman during her 11 days when
she could become a זבה, zavah, the principle is like this: if
a woman has uterine bleeding even from an outside source, even if
it's somehow stimulated by something external to her, if it's uterine bleeding,
she still is a נדה. But if it is bleeding during the
זבה zavah period due to, only during the זבה zavah period due
to the fact that she's pregnant and in the process of giving
birth, she does not become a זבה. zavah. Okay, so that's זובה
לאו מחמת ולד, zova lav machamat vlad, not because of childbirth. Now
how do you, what is defined as bleeding due to childbirth? So
she has to be in labor and the bleeding is accompanying the
labor, and the birth comes right after the bleeding, right, you know?
So during this period she's in pain and labor and she's bleeding,
and then she gives birth. Then we say she's not a זבה
zavah because the bleeding came as a result of the labor and
of the fetus. But if she was in pain and bleeding, but
then there was a break, there was, you know, a relief and
she went 24 hours or whatever we'll see a certain period of
time without pain and so on, and then she gave birth. So
the birth did not immediately follow the pain and the bleeding, there
was a little bit of a break. Then we say she is
a זבה. zavah. So the only thing that gets her out of
being a זבה zavah is bleeding during that period when it's with
childbirth pain leading straight into the birth. Okay, and then there's a
question of how big of a break has to occur to make
her into a זבה, zavah, to say that it's no longer part
of the birth. Okay, so let's read that. הישתה שלושה ימים. hishtah
shlosha yamim. She had three days of childbirth pains and therefore three
days of bleeding, which would make her a זבה zavah בתוך אחד
עשר יום, betoch achad asar yom, and it's during the 11 days
that would make her a זבה. zavah. אם שפתה מעת לעת, im
shaftah me-eis le-eis, if she had a relief for 24 hours וילדה
ve-yaldah and then she gave birth, so since there was 24 hours
between the last pain and the giving of the birth, it means
that we don't see the bleeding as due to the birth, והרי
זו יולדת בזוב, ve-harei zu yoledes be-zov, she's not only a יולדת,
yoledes, she's also a זבה. zavah. דברי רבי אליעזר. divrei Rabbi Eliezer.
That's Rabbi Eliezer. רבי יהושע אומר, Rabbi Yehoshua omer, no, לילה ויום
כליל שבת ויומו. lailah va-yom ke-leil Shabbos ve-yomo. It's not enough that
it's 24 hours. It's only if it was day and night, a
full day and a full night. and the night preceded the day.
Okay, so she's only would become a זבה zovah if the break
was that there was first a full nighttime without pain and then
a full day without pain. And only then, so he's more מקל.
meikel. He says that it'll be harder for her to be a
זבה. zovah. Okay, you need a bigger break for her to be
a זבה. zovah. Okay, and ושבתה מן הצער ולא מן הדם. v'shavsa
min hatzaar v'lo min hadam. The break has to be not that
she stopped bleeding, but that she stopped having the pain during this
period of time. Only with that break in the pain during for
this time of night and then day would she become a זבה.
zovah. Anyway, so they're debating that. So that's an area of debate
and that's an area where one person would say she's a זבה,
zovah, another would say she's not a זבה, zovah, and that could
be a debate that leads to again a חטאת of a חייב
כרת. chayav kareis. Let's just try to do a little bit more
here. בין דין לדין, בין דיני ממונות דיני נפשות דיני מכות. bein
dinei mamonus dinei nefashos dinei makkos. So what would be a case
like this?
דיני ממונות, dinei mamonus בפלוגתא דשמואל ורבי אבהו, b'plugta d'Shmuel v'Rabbi Abahu,
דאמר שמואל. d'amar Shmuel. So now we make it not just about
a substantive law of a monetary issue, but about the adjudication of
a monetary issue. שמואל Shmuel says שנים שדנו דיניהם דין אלא שנקראו
בית דין חצוף. shnayim she'danu dineihen din, ella shenikra'u beis din chatzuf.
If you have two people on a דיני ממונות dinei mamonus case,
it's good. It was a little חוצפהדיק, chutzpadik, okay, but it's a
good valid judgment. ורבי אבהו אומר לדברי הכל אין דיניהם דין. v'Rabbi
Abahu omeir l'divrei hakol ein dineihen din. It's not binding. Now, here's
the first case where it's not at all obvious, what does this
have to do with a חייב כרת? chayav kareis? We're debating whether
it was a good judgment on a דיני ממונות dinei mamonus. case.
So רש"י Rashi says here's the issue. Okay, Dave and I are
debating whether I don't know whether this is my iPhone or Dave's.
We go to a בית דין beis din of two and בית
דין rules that it's mine. Great. Now I go ahead and I
take this iPhone and I marry a woman with it. הרי את
מקודשת לי harei at mekudeshes li with this iPhone. Okay, and then
that woman goes and sleeps with somebody. Alright, so if the ruling
of the בית דין was correct, then that woman is my wife
and she's committed adultery and that leads to a weighty sin. If
the ruling of the בית דין was not valid because it was
a בית דין of two and not three, then it was your
iPhone, it was never mine, the woman was never married, and therefore
she never committed adultery. So any debate about a ממונות issue could
always be a debate about that could lead to a weighty sin
of כרת or worse or worse if I use that money to
go marry a woman. Okay, so that's the case of דיני ממונות.
Now, דיני נפשות בפלוגתא
דרבי
ורבנן דתניא רבי אומר. dinei nefashos b'plugta d'Rabbi v'rabbanan d'tanya Rabbi omeir.
So again, ונתתה נפש תחת נפש. v'nasata nefesh tachas nafesh.
It's so funny that this is where we go. Remember the case
where somebody tried to kill ראובן Reuven and killed שמעון Shimon, and
do you have to pay damages for שמעון's Shimon death, wrongful death
damages? So רבי says the case was assault tried to kill ראובן
Reuven and killed שמעון, נפש תחת נפש ממון, nefesh tachas nafesh mammon,
that you have to pay damages. את אומר ממון ואינו אלא נפש,
at omeir mammon v'eino ela nefesh, maybe it means that you actually
are executed when you try to kill ראובן Reuven and kill שמעון
ממש, mamash, שנאמר ונתנו sheniamar v'nasnu it says pay when it's a
miscarriage, ונאמר ונתנו למטה v'neiamar v'nasnu l'mata and it says giving here,
מה להלן ממון mah hahallan mammon the same way by the miscarriage
it means payment, אף כאן here when it says a life for
a life, ממון mammon it means payment. So how does the and
וחכמים v'chachamim would say no, in that case the person is either
executed or even if they're not executed, it's קים ליה בדרבה מיניה,
kim lei b'drabba minei, there's no payment. So again, there's a dispute
about is there payment? But that could be a case of a
חייב כרת chayav kareis if that money that was supposed to be
paid is now used to marry a woman. Okay, so that's how
they're debating. It's very funny that that's what we make the dispute
of דיני נפשות dinei nefashos about. Ultimately we turn the דיני נפשות
dispute to be a question of payment. Why don't we just have
it as a debate about whether somebody really is liable the death
penalty or not? I don't know, maybe anyway.
Okay. דיני מכות בפלוגתא דרבי ישמעאל ורבנן דתנן מכות בשלושה. dinei makkos
b'plugta d'Rabbi Yishmael v'rabbanan d'tnan makkos b'shlosha. You administer lashes with three.
משום רבי ישמעאל אמרו בעשרים ושלושה. mishum Rabbi Yishmael amru b'esrim v'shlosha.
Okay, so again it's more about the
adjudication than it is about the question of liability or not. What
does this have to
do with a case of a חייב כרת? chayav kareis? Not exactly
clear what this has to do with a case of a חייב
כרת. chayav kareis. So רש"י Rashi says let me remind myself what
רש"י Rashi says. Right, so רש"י Rashi says if they gave him
lashes with a בית דין of three and you said that was
not legitimate, you needed a בית דין of twenty-three, then the person
who got lashes is entitled for compensation because he got given lashes
by a court which was not legitimate. So since he's entitled for
compensation, if he takes that money and uses it to marry a
woman etc etc etc. So if you can turn anything into money,
you can turn it into a question of you know חייב כרת
chayav kareis or חייב מיתה chayav misa because money was used to
marry a woman. Okay do it. Okay. בין נגעי אדם לנגעי בתים
נגעי בגדים, bein nig'ei adam l'nig'ei batim nig'ei begadim,
so בין נגע לנגע a צרעת tzaraas, question. So נגעי אדם is
the פלוגתא דרבי יהושע ורבנן דתנן. plugta d'Rabbi Yehoshua v'rabbanan d'tnan.
This is the famous debate.
אם בהרת קודם לשיער לבן. im baheres kodem l'sea'ar lavan. טמא. tamei.
So if the Torah says that a בהרת, baheres, a type of
a spot,
and then the white hair, right, is like a סימן siman of
טומאה. tumah So it says which came first. So if he has
a hair first, the spot first and then the white hair, טמא.
tamei. אם שער לבן קודם לבהרת, im sear lavan kodem labaheres, but
if first there was the white hair and then there was the
spot, טהור. tahor. ספק, safek, if it's a debate which came first,
טמא. tamei. So the person is טמא. tamei רבי יהושע אומר Rabbi
Yehoshua omer כהה. keiha. It's light. מאי כהה? mai keiha? What does
that mean? אמר רבא amar Rava כהה טהור. keiha tahor. It's his
way of saying that he disagrees and it's טהור. tahor. So since
they debate what happens if there's a ספק, safek, okay, is the
person טמא tamei or טהור tahor from צרעת, tzaraas that's a scenario
of debating a צרעת tzaraas case. Now, how does that turn into
a חיוב מיתה? chiyuv misa? So רש"י Rashi says well, you know,
if a guy who's a מצורע goes into the בית המקדש Beis
HaMikdash or חיוב כרת, chiyuv kares, etc., etc., that could be a
case of חיוב כרת chiyuv kares if you go into the בית
המקדש Beis HaMikdash, or other possible scenarios that I'm not going into
because that's actually disputable because that's not a חייב חטאת, that's like
whatever. Anyway, we'll just leave it at that. Okay.
Let's just get to the end of the דף.
נגעי בתים, what's the debate about a צרעת of the house? בפלוגתא
דרבי אליעזר ברבי שמעון ורבנן. b'plugta d'Rabbi Eliezer berabbi Shimon v'Rabanan. תנן,
tnan, רבי אליעזר ברבי שמעון אומר Rabbi Eliezer berabbi Shimon omer לעולם
אין הבית טמא עד שיראה כשני גריסין על שתי אבנים בשתי כתלים
בקרן זוית, l'olam ein habayis tamei ad sheyeira'eh kishnei gerisim al shtei
avanim bishtei ktalim bekern zavis, right?
So basically he says because it says קיר kir and וקירות, kiros,
the only type of way you get a house that's טמא tamei.
is you have a wall, two walls that are like one wall,
so you have a corner and you have the spot that goes
right around the corner. That's what he says. So let's read that.
עד שיראה כשני גריסין, ad sheyeira'eh kishnei gerisim, it has to be
the size of two beans because each spot is the size of
one bean. על שתי אבנים, al shtei avanim, it has to be
on two stones, בשתי כתלים, bishtei ktalim, on two walls, בקרן זוית,
bekern zavis, in a corner. ארכו כשני גריסין, archo kishnei gerisim, the
length is two beans, רחבו כגריס, rovcho kegris, and the width is
one bean, right? Because one bean times two is two beans length,
one bean bean high. מאי טעמא דרבי אליעזר ברבי שמעון, mai ta'ama
d'Rabbi Eliezer berabbi Shimon, what's his reason? כתיב קיר ksiv kir and
it's written וקירות, v'kiros, walls. איזו קיר שהיא כקירות? eizu kir shehi
k'kiros? הוי אומר זה קרן זוית, hevei omer zeh kern zavis, it's
the corner.
So again, they're debating, he would say the house is טהור tahor
unless it exactly fits those parameters. The רבנן Rabanan would say the
house is טמא. So a dispute about טומאה tumah could ultimately lead
to a case of a חיוב כרת chiyuv kares or a חטאת,
you know, going into the בית המקדש, although that's not a חטאת,
or other types of scenarios where a טומאה dispute could lead to
this. נגעי בגדים, let's end with this, leprosy of clothes. בפלוגתא דרבי
נתן בן אבטולמוס ורבנן. b'plugta d'Rabbi Nosson ben Avtulmos v'Rabanan. דתנן, d'tnan,
רבי נתן בן אבטולמוס אומר, Rabbi Nosson ben Avtulmos omer, מנין לפריחה
בבגדים שהיא טהורה? minayin l'pricha b'vgadim shehi tahorah?
Let's say you have a spot of leprosy on a garment and
then it spread and it covered the entire garment. So he claims
oh, now it's טהור. tahor. How do I know it's טהור? tahor?
נאמר קרחת וגבחת באדם, ne'emar kerachas v'gabachas b'adam,
it says a bald spot and whatever, a spot by a person,
ונאמר קרחת וגבחת בבגד v'ne'emar kerachas v'gabachas b'vaged and it says by
clothes. מה להלן פרחה בכולו טהור, mah lehalan parcha b'kulo tahor, the
same way we know the principle by a person is if the
leprosy covers him from the top of his head to the bottom
he's טהור, tahor, אף כאן פרחה בכולו טהור, af kan parcha b'kulo
tahor, here too he's טהור. tahor. And then we are going to
continue tomorrow. I won't be here on יום טוב. Yom Tov. Going
through, you know, all of these things and how they link to
debates of תנאים Tannaim and that could be the debate of the
זקן ממרא and then רש"י points out how that ultimately could turn
into something that's a weighty sin according to רבי מאיר, you need
a weighty sin of חיוב כרת chiyuv kares and bringing a חטאת.
Okay, we will end here. Have a good יום טוב Yom Tov
everybody. גוט יום טוב. Gut Yom Tov. Who's going to start?